José Jair Santanna

Ph.D. Researcher, Lecturer, Network Security Specialist & (Big) Data Analyst

Contact

Drienerlolaan 5, Zilverling 5110, 7522 NB Enschede, The Netherlands.

+31 (6) 42330703

http://jairsantanna.com j.i.santanna@utwente.nl

Languages

portuguese native english fluency spanish comprehension dutch comprehension

Programming

Bash, Python, C#,SQL PIG, Spark & Impala

Professional Objective

A research & development position with focus on network security and the use of big data technologies to improve network data analysis. A position where I can transfer my enthusiasm, knowledge, skills and experience into meaningful innovation that improve the security in computer networks, specially in the Internet.

Education

2013–Now **Doctor** in Computer Science University of Twente, The Netherlands

"The DDoS as a \$ervice Phenomenon".

2010-2012 **Master** in Computer Science Federal University of Rio Grande do Sul, Brazil

"A BPM-based Solution for Inter-domain Circuit Management". The outcome of this work generated a product still in use by the Brazilian National Education

and Research Network (RNP) (Link: http://meican.cipo.rnp.br/).

2005–2010 **Bachelor** in Computer Engineer Federal University of Pará, Brazi

"A Comparative Evaluation of DCCP Protocol in a Experimental Mesh Network."

Experience

Technical Adviser

2016 To the Dutch National Cyber Security Center and the Scientific Research & Documen-

n Center

For the production of a report on "Cyber metrics 2016: DDoS and Malware"

requested by the Dutch Ministry of Security and Justice.

2016 To the Yokohama National University Japan

For the production of a report on "Reflection & Amplification DDoS attacks" requested by the *Japanese Ministry of Internal Affairs and Communications*.

Assistant Professor

2012–2013 University of Santa Cruz do Sul (UNISC)

Santa Cruz do Sul, Brazil

Tasks & Responsibilities: Supervise students and teach the following courses: Computer Networks, Computer Network Management, and Digital Systems.

Guest Lecturer

2015 & 2016 Product Design to Online Business (course) University of Twente, The Netherlands

Audience: bachelor students of industrial engineering and business information

technology.

2015 **Network Security (course)** University of Twente, The Netherlands

Audience: master and bachelor students of computer science, electrical engineer, and telematics from the University of Twente, 3TU cyber security, and

members of ICT labs.

2015 **Cybercrime & Cybersecurity (minor)** University of Twente, The Netherlands

Audience: bachelor students from University of Twente, European Research Center for Information (ERCIS), Westfälische Wilhelms - Univerität Münster, Uni-

versität Innsbruck, and University of Leicester.

Software Developer

2015-Now Distributed Denial of Service Attacks Database (DDoSDB)

Link: http://bit.ly/ddos_db

An initiative to develop the largest open database with DDoS attacks.

Languages: Python, Bash, Pig Latin & Apache Impala

2010–2011 Management Environment of Inter-domain Circuits for Advanced Networks (MEICAN)

Link: http://meican.cipo.rnp.br/

Development of an Executable Network Management Policies Editor sponsored

by the Brazilian National Education and Research Network (RNP).

Language: WS-BPEL

2009 Support for Planning Sustainable Electrical Power Generation via Vegetable Oil.

Desktop application sponsored by Eletronorte, subsidiary of the major Brazilian

power utility (Eletrobrás). Language: C#.Net & mySQL

Student Supervisor

[M.Sc. Degree] Joey de Vries [Cum Laude], Justyna Chromik [Cum Laude], Wouter de Vries, Mark Wierbosch, and Jarmo van Lenthe.

[B.Sc. Degree] Roeland Krak, Max Kerkers, Dirk Maan, Jochum Börger, and Guilherme Dressler.

International Conference Reviewer

IFIP Networking (2014–2016), IEEE/IFIP Network Operations and Management Symposium (2014 & 2016), Asia-Pacific Network Operations and Management Symposium (2013 & 2014), IFIP/IEEE Integrated Management (2015), International Conference on Autonomous Infrastructure, Management and Security (2015), International Conference on Network and Service Management (2013–2015), EUNICE Conference (2013) & IEEE Symposium on Computers and Communications (2011).

Awards

| 2015 | Best Ph.D. 'Elevator Pitch' | (1 st Place) | CTIT Symposium, University of Twente |
|------|----------------------------------|----------------------------|--|
| 2015 | Best Poster (3 rd Place) | | CTIT Symposium, University of Twente |
| 2015 | Best Paper Award | Autonomous Infrastructure, | Management and Security Conference |
| 2015 | Top Papers Nomination Bra | zilian Symposium on Comp | uter Networks and Distributed Systems |
| 2010 | Student Award (3 rd Place) | Computer En | gineer, Federal University of Pará, Brazil |

Communication Skills

More than 30 presentations in the last 3 years (see in: http://www.slideshare.net/jjcsantanna), among those I highlight:

| 2015 | Oral Presentation | at Logius (part of the Dutch Ministry of the Interior and Kingdom Relations). |
|-------------|--------------------------|---|
| 2015 | Oral Presentation | to the Dutch National Management Organization of Internet Providers (NBIP). |
| 2015 | Oral Presentation | to the Dutch National Cyber Security Centrum (NCSC). |
| 2013 & 2015 | Oral Presentation | at the 31^{th} and 36^{th} IRTF Network Management Research Group (NMRG). |

Scientific Appendix

Description of Ph.D. Research Publications